Welcome to Respiratory Tract Pathology.
The first section is the nasopharynx.
The first disorder to discuss is rhinitis.
Rhinitis basically is inflammation of the nasomucosa.
You know that the nasomucosa is lined by respiratory-type epithelium.
Adenovirus is the most common cause.
This classically presents with sneezing, congestion, and runny nose,
so basically your common cold.
Again, adenovirus being the most common cause.
It is also possible to get an allergic rhinitis,
and this would be an inflammation of the nasomucosa
due to a type 1 hypersensitivity reaction.
And, of course, with a type 1 hypersensitivity reaction,
we're going to be looking for an antigen,
and in this particular case you'll find one.
For example, pollen would be something that could elicit an allergic rhinitis.
Because this is an allergic-type reaction,
it's going to be inflammation with eosinophils,
and it's going to be associated with other types of atopic disorders
such as asthma and eczema.
Now, one of the consequences of rhinitis,
and this is probably the most high yield in this particular discussion,
is that you can get nasal polyps.
So patients who have repeated bouts of rhinitis,
they develop nasal polyps.
And a polyp, again, is just a protrusion of edematous-inflamed nasal mucosa.
All right, now here comes the high yield.
The first high yield is that if you have a child with nasal polyps,
you really want to think cystic fibrosis.
Again, very high yield.
If you have a child with nasal polyps,
you want to test that child for cystic fibrosis,
and that becomes particularly high yield for examination purposes.
The second high yield here is that there are a subgroup of adults
who also develop nasal polyps
because they have something called aspirin-intolerant asthma.
This is a triad of asthma, aspirin-induced bronchospasm, and nasal polyps.
And it's seen in 10% of asthmatic adults.
So remember that patients with aspirin-intolerant asthma
can also develop nasal polyps.
So those are the two high yields on this slide.
The next disorder is angiofibroma.
Angio means blood vessel, fibro means fibrous tissue,
and of course, oma means mass.
So this is a benign tumor of the nasal mucosa
comprised of blood vessels and fibrous tissue.
Again, the name gives it away.
Now, one important thing, and very high yield,
it's only seen in adolescent males.
That's the classic demographic.
It is very, very, very rare in a female.
So for your purposes, it's basically a tumor of adolescent males.
And these can bleed because of the large blood vessels,
and so they can present with profuse epistaxis,
and that's the classic presentation, especially on examinations.
Nasopharyngeal carcinoma
is a malignant tumor of nasopharyngeal epithelium.
Of course, it's arising from the nasopharynx,
hence it's nasopharyngeal,
and it is epithelium, hence the word carcinoma.
So the name really tells you a lot there.
Now, basically, this is an EBV-driven tumor.
That's particularly high yield.
Also high yield to know is that
it usually arises in two demographics,
African children and Chinese young adults.
The classic presentation is that
they give you, especially on examinations,
a Chinese adult who has enlarged cervical lymph nodes
because this tumor usually can spread
to the cervical lymph nodes very quickly,
and it classically presents
with involvement of the cervical lymph nodes.
A biopsy is then performed,
and the biopsy shows this classic finding,
which is pleomorphic epithelial cells
in a background of lymphocytes.
Now, these epithelial cells are scattered
within the background of lymphocytes,
and so often you have to prove
that they're actually epithelial,
and so keratin is often performed in these
to ensure that there is a carcinoma.
And so it's very high yield
for purposes of board examination
to know that this is the histology,
and what they like to tell you
is that there's a Chinese male
he presents with cervical adenopathy,
a biopsy is performed,
and that the pathology report says
that there is pleomorphic keratin-positive cells.
Of course, keratin-positive means
that these are epithelial,
because keratin is the intermediate filament
in epithelial cells,
and so once you have keratin-positive cells,
you know that you're dealing with a carcinoma.
And so nasopharyngeal carcinoma
is a classic entity you think about
with this particular story.
As far as the larynx is concerned,
the first disorder is acute epiglottitis.
Acute epiglottitis refers to
inflammation of the epiglottis.
The most common cause is H-flu, type B,
and this is the most common cause
both in immunized and in non-immunized children.
So H-flu, type B, is the most common cause
in both immunized and non-immunized children.
Now you're well aware of the fact
that the epiglottis sits at the back of the throat
behind the tongue,
and so you get inflammation,
massive inflammation of the earway,
and so you can see
what an inflamed epiglottis might look like,
and the patients will present
with high fever, sore throat,
because of the inflammation in that region,
and then they get drooling with dysphagia
because of the fact that the epiglottis is swollen,
and hence the airway is compromised.
They have a muffled voice
because they're speaking
with something in the back of their throat,
and they have inspiratory stridor
because of, again, the compromise to the airway.
And this is really the key thing
that you have to worry about,
which is that there's a risk
of acute airway obstruction.
So this disorder is a medical emergency
because you need to protect the airway
in these patients.
Next disorder, laryngotracheobronchitis.
So, again, the name tells you
that you're getting inflammation
of the upper airway.
Most common cause is parainfluenza virus,
and these are the patients
that classically present
with this hoarse barking cough
and then an inspiratory stridor.
So that's laryngotracheobronchitis.
Vocal cord nodules are nodules
that arise on the vocal cord,
and it's classically due to excessive use.
So because it's due to excessive use,
it's often bilateral.
So you'll see one next to the other.
These are composed of degenerative
myxoid connective tissue,
and it's going to present with hoarseness
because of the disruption to the vocal cord.
Now, this is a wear and tear issue,
and so it occurs because the patients
have had excessive use,
and, of course, it will resolve with rest.
Here's what it looks like.
You can see one vocal cord nodule here,
another one here,
and these are bilateral
because of the fact that it's due to
a wear and tear or use-related problem.
Now, here's what you see
if you were to do the histology,
and all I'm trying to highlight here
is that you get myxoid degeneration
of the connective tissue,
which leads to the formation
of this vocal cord nodule.
Laryngeal papilloma is actually
a tumor of the vocal cord.
You get a papillary or finger-like projection
off the vocal cord,
and it's benign.
Of course, it's very important to know
that it's due to HPV 6 and 11.
That's high yield.
Laryngeal papilloma HPV 6 and 11.
Of course, because it's HPV,
it's going to be associated
with coelocytic change
where you're to see it on biopsy.
Very high yield to know
that laryngeal papilloma is single in adults.
It's usually one single lesion in adults,
but that in children, it's multiple.
And of course, because you have disruption
to the vocal cord,
it's going to present with hoarseness.
Laryngeal carcinoma is a squamous cell carcinoma
that arises from the lining of the vocal cord.
Recall that the vocal cord is actually lined
by squamous epithelium,
and so it's not anything special here
that laryngeal carcinoma would be
a squamous cell carcinoma.
You're well aware of the two risk factors,
alcohol and tobacco.
Those are the two key risk factors
for laryngeal carcinoma.
Now, it's important to note that rarely
you can get laryngeal carcinoma
from a laryngeal papilloma.
Remember from the prior slide
that laryngeal papillomas are due to HPV 6 and 11.
Remember that 6 and 11 are low risk HPVs.
Now, remember, we don't call them zero risk.
We call them low risk.
There is a risk for cancer, but it's very low.
So it is possible to get laryngeal carcinoma
from HPV 6 and 11,
but again, that would be rare.
Of course, because you've got disruption
to the vocal cord, you're going to get hoarseness
and other signs of advanced disease
would be cough and stridor.
And so these are some of the key presenting signs
with laryngeal carcinoma.
And that concludes this particular section.